<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Home on Roman Böhm</title><link>/</link><description>Recent content in Home on Roman Böhm</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Bulk Import Into Safari's Reading List</title><link>/til/bulk-add-to-safari-reading-list/</link><pubDate>Thu, 28 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/til/bulk-add-to-safari-reading-list/</guid><description>Problem I had recently dissolved some third-party reading list of mine and wanted to migrate all these yet unread articles and blog posts into Safari&amp;rsquo;s reading list. I was looking for some kind of bulk import functionality in Safari itself, but only found the option to add multiple tabs to the reading list. With my former list containing over 300 items, that wasn&amp;rsquo;t the way to go.
Solution Luckily, MacOS&amp;rsquo; Notes app offers a way to bypass the need to open hundreds of tabs, provided you have the reading list items available as a new line-separated list of links.</description></item><item><title>Use Mastodon as a Comment System</title><link>/til/mastodon-comments/</link><pubDate>Sat, 23 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/til/mastodon-comments/</guid><description>Problem I wanted to have a comment system for the posts in this blog. Not because I think there&amp;rsquo;s demand for it, but because I can. 😎
Solution The first thing which came to my mind was abusing Mastodon&amp;rsquo;s toot system for my comment system. And of course, I (luckily) wasn&amp;rsquo;t the first person to have that idea. Daniel Pecos provided both a detailed instructional post as well as webcomponent to embed Mastodon discussion on one&amp;rsquo;s site.</description></item><item><title>Frictionless SSH for VS Code Dev Containers on MacOS</title><link>/til/vs-code-devcontainer-ssh/</link><pubDate>Fri, 30 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/til/vs-code-devcontainer-ssh/</guid><description>Introduction I wanted to write down how I got a frictionless SSH setup for VS Code Dev Containers on MacOS where I have the necessary keys available, but don&amp;rsquo;t need to manually unlock them anymore. I can e.g. simply push to GitHub/pull from GitHub from my dev environment inside the container.
Setup SSH Key(s) I usually create a separate SSH key pair for every use case. That means my ~/.ssh dir contains a dedicated key for GitHub, which I&amp;rsquo;ll use as an example in the remainder of the post:</description></item><item><title>Using a Manitu Domain for iCloud Mail</title><link>/til/icloud-mail-manitu-domain/</link><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/til/icloud-mail-manitu-domain/</guid><description>Introduction How to: Set up a custom domain for iCloud mail using a Manitu domain
I&amp;rsquo;m using the German hoster Manitu for the romanboehm.com domain. I also have an iCloud+ subscription allowing me to use this domain for iCloud mail. I found the process of setting that up quite under-supported on both iCloud and Manitu&amp;rsquo;s side, so I wanted to document it. A German-speaking blogger named Steven Kaminsky apparently had encountered the same pains in the past, and the linked post was of great help, but I still wanted to quickly persist my notes on the process and highlight potential hiccups with Manitu especially.</description></item><item><title>How to: Distribute a Java Source File on GitHub</title><link>/posts/how-to-distribute-a-java-source-file-on-github/</link><pubDate>Sun, 08 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/how-to-distribute-a-java-source-file-on-github/</guid><description>Update 2023-04-18 The below post is relevant anymore only for historic reasons. Contrary to my statement below, JReleaser does indeed offer the possibility to distribute source files, basically in a single line. In combination with the Maven Release plugin, I was able to standardize the whole workflow, which made distributing JsonWheel.java and upgrading versions much easier.
Introduction For my single-source-file-no-dependencies JSON parser for the JVM, JSON Wheel, I was looking for a better way for distribution other than a bunch of convoluted, homegrown shell scripts, or modifying and uploading files manually to GitHub releases.</description></item><item><title>Use Raw HTML in Hugo's Markdown</title><link>/til/hugo-raw-html/</link><pubDate>Mon, 02 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/til/hugo-raw-html/</guid><description>Problem I want the link to this blog in my Mastodon profile to be &amp;ldquo;verified&amp;rdquo; (green) link. This is done by adding a custom anchor element somewhere on the site:
&amp;lt;a rel=&amp;#39;me&amp;#39; href=&amp;#39;https://mastodon.social/@romanboehm&amp;#39;&amp;gt;Mastodon&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt; By default, however, Hugo, the static site generator of my choice, does not permit this.
Solution If you don&amp;rsquo;t like to activate the renderer&amp;rsquo;s unsafe mode in order to be able to insert raw html, you can achieve this with so-called shortcodes:</description></item><item><title>Custom Shortcuts For Any Web Editor</title><link>/til/custom-shortcuts/</link><pubDate>Sat, 17 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/til/custom-shortcuts/</guid><description>Problem Confluence and Jira, at the least in the versions we use at my work, do not offer shortcuts for monospace formatting. You can type two opening curly brackets followed by &amp;lt;text&amp;gt; followed by two closing curly brackets, and that will render &amp;lt;text&amp;gt; monospaced. But that does not work for applying formatting later one.
Solution There&amp;rsquo;s a nice, generic workaround for problems like these: Bookmarklets. They live as bookmarks in your browser, but you can see them as buttons being able to execute JavaScript on click.</description></item><item><title>Using Third Party Email Aliases With iCloud Mail on iOS/iPadOS</title><link>/til/mail-alias-ios-ipados/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/til/mail-alias-ios-ipados/</guid><description>How to: Use Third Party Email Aliases With iCloud Mail on iOS/iPadOS
My primary mail account is with Posteo, a privacy-focused provider from Germany. I don&amp;rsquo;t intend to change that, they&amp;rsquo;re great and deserve every support!
Also, I&amp;rsquo;m using Apple&amp;rsquo;s operating systems almost exclusively and subscribe to iCloud. iCloud and third party mail aren&amp;rsquo;t a great match, unfortunately.
So for a long time I couldn&amp;rsquo;t figure out how to use my iCloud account to both receive and send mail through my posteo.</description></item><item><title>How to: Configure Multiple DataSources in Spring Boot</title><link>/posts/how-to-configure-multiple-datasources-in-spring-boot/</link><pubDate>Tue, 16 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/how-to-configure-multiple-datasources-in-spring-boot/</guid><description>Introduction A few days ago a colleague of mine and I wanted to know &amp;ldquo;[w]hat’s the Spring Boot way of defining three different DataSources through externalized config (application.yaml), with each sharing the same Hikari settings?&amp;rdquo; That is: We basically had a working solution, we just weren&amp;rsquo;t sure it was how you&amp;rsquo;d do it making use of all the goodness Spring Boot offers. Therefore I consequently tried offloading the task of figuring it out to Twitter.</description></item><item><title>Tell Me Your Environment and I Tell You What Your Context Is</title><link>/posts/tell-me-your-environment-and-i-tell-you-what-your-context-is/</link><pubDate>Sat, 06 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/tell-me-your-environment-and-i-tell-you-what-your-context-is/</guid><description>Introduction At my previous work we had this problem where we couldn&amp;rsquo;t run through our entire workflow in our integration system because we were missing the necessary input data to some central service&amp;rsquo;s integration instance. We therefore took it upon us to provide said data by asynchronously mirroring data from prod to int.
This is definitely not a &amp;ldquo;Five tips on how to deal with numbers in JavaScript &amp;ndash; NaN will shock you!</description></item><item><title>Harry Logger and the Message with the Garbled Pattern</title><link>/posts/harry-logger-and-the-message-with-the-garbled-pattern/</link><pubDate>Wed, 12 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/harry-logger-and-the-message-with-the-garbled-pattern/</guid><description>Introduction I know &amp;rsquo;twas the season (of problems with logging), but this post is definitely not about the recent log4j 2.x vulnerabilities. With that out of the way&amp;hellip;
Have you ever woken up and wondered &amp;ldquo;How can a combination of a specific log message in a Java app, log4j, journald, and Filebeat corrupt logs downstream?&amp;rdquo; No? Good, me neither. That should not be something to worry about, and yet it was for my team and me at work recently.</description></item><item><title>Keep Your Properties Close, but Your @TestConfiguration Closer - Selected Spring Boot Testing Tips</title><link>/posts/keep-your-properties-close-but-your-@testconfiguration-closer-selected-spring-boot-testing-tips/</link><pubDate>Sat, 02 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/keep-your-properties-close-but-your-@testconfiguration-closer-selected-spring-boot-testing-tips/</guid><description>Introduction Spring Boot is great and the best thing about it is how easy it makes it to test your application. So here are some selected tips for writing tests with Spring Boot. The most recent stable Spring Boot version at the time of publishing was 2.5.5.
Keep Configuration Close to the Tests The configuration and setup of the tests should be as close to them as possible. This reduces the possibility of one test interfering with another and makes it much easier for the reader of the test to grok its purpose.</description></item><item><title>Ubuntu and Nvidia Optimus</title><link>/til/optimus-ubuntu/</link><pubDate>Mon, 06 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/til/optimus-ubuntu/</guid><description>How to: Make Nvidia Optimus work after installing Ubuntu 21.04.
I own a Thinkpad T480 with a dedicated GPU (Nvidia Geforce MX 150) in addition to the onboard Intel GPU. The easiest way to have a Linux distribution with full Optimus support running would be to download the most recent PopOS! image with the proprietary Nvidia drivers baked in.
Since I cannot stand some of the modifications System76 made to Gnome I just want to get the most recent Ubuntu (or Kubuntu) version and go from there.</description></item><item><title>Meta Militia, or: Using a Custom Domain with GitHub Pages</title><link>/posts/meta-militia-or-using-a-custom-domain-with-github-pages/</link><pubDate>Wed, 16 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/posts/meta-militia-or-using-a-custom-domain-with-github-pages/</guid><description>How to: Using a custom domain (apex domain and www subdomain) for a Hugo-generated page hosted on GitHub Pages.
Introduction What better first post than a meta post detailing the experience of getting my page running under my own domain in the first place. On the true developer-scale probably right below writing your own custom static site generator (in Rust or Kotlin, of course). If you&amp;rsquo;re too cheap for the all-inclusive Wordpress experience, too vain to just use the &amp;lt;username&amp;gt;.</description></item><item><title>About Roman Böhm</title><link>/about/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/about/</guid><description>Roman Böhm is a software engineer living in Würzburg, Germany. He is mostly interested in Java, the JVM, the Spring framework, RDBMs, and producing boring yet stable software.
After finishing his B. Eng. in Computer Science at THWS Würzburg in 2019 with distinction, he went on to work for Flyeralarm GmbH Würzburg where he sped up a distributed system guiding several thousand orders a day into print.
In 2022, Roman moved on to be a Senior Software Engineer, as of 2023 Technical Lead, for sprd.</description></item></channel></rss>