<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Icloud on Roman Böhm</title><link>/tags/icloud/</link><description>Recent content in Icloud on Roman Böhm</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 25 Jun 2023 10:56:28 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/icloud/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Using a Manitu Domain for iCloud Mail</title><link>/til/icloud-mail-manitu-domain/</link><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/til/icloud-mail-manitu-domain/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="introduction">Introduction&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>How to: Set up a custom domain for iCloud mail using a Manitu domain&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;m using the German hoster &lt;a href="https://www.manitu.de">Manitu&lt;/a> for the romanboehm.com domain. I also have an iCloud+ subscription &lt;a href="https://www.icloud.com/icloudplus/customdomain">allowing me to use this domain for iCloud mail&lt;/a>. I found the process of setting that up quite under-supported on both iCloud and Manitu&amp;rsquo;s side, so I wanted to document it. &lt;a href="https://bazomg.de/index.php/2022/01/eigene-domain-in-icloud-mail-nutzen/">A German-speaking blogger named Steven Kaminsky apparently had encountered the same pains in the past&lt;/a>, and the linked post was of great help, but I still wanted to quickly persist my notes on the process and highlight potential hiccups with Manitu especially. For my sake and fellow Manitu-with-iCloud+ users'.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Using Third Party Email Aliases With iCloud Mail on iOS/iPadOS</title><link>/til/mail-alias-ios-ipados/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/til/mail-alias-ios-ipados/</guid><description>&lt;p>How to: Use Third Party Email Aliases With iCloud Mail on iOS/iPadOS&lt;/p>
&lt;p>My primary mail account is with &lt;a href="https://www.posteo.de">Posteo&lt;/a>, a privacy-focused provider from Germany. I don&amp;rsquo;t intend to change that, they&amp;rsquo;re great and deserve every support!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Also, I&amp;rsquo;m using Apple&amp;rsquo;s operating systems almost exclusively and subscribe to iCloud. iCloud and third party mail aren&amp;rsquo;t a great match, unfortunately.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So for a long time I couldn&amp;rsquo;t figure out &lt;em>how to use my iCloud account to both receive and send mail through my posteo.de address&lt;/em>. On Android using Gmail that wasn&amp;rsquo;t hard: Forward mail to your Gmail account and register your posteo address as an alias. This alias was then available also in the Gmail app.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>