<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Macos on Roman Böhm</title><link>/tags/macos/</link><description>Recent content in Macos on Roman Böhm</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 28 Sep 2023 11:24:07 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/macos/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Bulk Import Into Safari's Reading List</title><link>/til/bulk-add-to-safari-reading-list/</link><pubDate>Thu, 28 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/til/bulk-add-to-safari-reading-list/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="problem">Problem&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>I had recently dissolved some third-party reading list of mine and wanted to migrate all these yet unread articles and blog posts into Safari&amp;rsquo;s reading list. I was looking for some kind of bulk import functionality in Safari itself, but only found the option to add multiple tabs to the reading list. With my former list containing over 300 items, that wasn&amp;rsquo;t the way to go.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="solution">Solution&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Luckily, MacOS&amp;rsquo; &lt;em>Notes&lt;/em> app offers a way to bypass the need to open hundreds of tabs, provided you have the reading list items available as a new line-separated list of links. If so, simply&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Frictionless SSH for VS Code Dev Containers on MacOS</title><link>/til/vs-code-devcontainer-ssh/</link><pubDate>Fri, 30 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/til/vs-code-devcontainer-ssh/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="introduction">Introduction&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>I wanted to write down how I got a frictionless SSH setup for &lt;a href="https://code.visualstudio.com/docs/devcontainers/containers">VS Code Dev Containers&lt;/a> on MacOS where I have the necessary keys available, but don&amp;rsquo;t need to manually unlock them anymore. I can e.g. simply push to GitHub/pull from GitHub from my dev environment inside the container.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="setup">Setup&lt;/h2>
&lt;h3 id="ssh-keys">SSH Key(s)&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>I usually create a separate SSH key pair for every use case. That means my &lt;code>~/.ssh&lt;/code> dir contains a dedicated key for GitHub, which I&amp;rsquo;ll use as an example in the remainder of the post:&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>